Actions

zeptoscript does not support multitasking itself (non-zeptoscript tasks can execute, but only one zeptoscript environment can exist, in only one task), so in its place zeptoscript has actions, like zeptoforth actions, to provide asynchronous execution with a single task.

Actions belong to schedules, one of which may execute in a given task at a time. Within a schedule actions execute in a cooperative, round-robin fashion. They may also send messages to and receive messages from each other. An action may only send a single message to or receive a single message from one another at a time. Messaging is strictly synchronous; an action will not continue executing after sending a message until the message is received, sending the message times out, or sending the message otherwise fails (e.g. the target action terminates).

Actions all share the same stack as one another; persistent state belonging to an action is achieved through binding values (e.g. a record or object) to the states as closures or through globals. Also note that operations set for actions only occur after the handler for the current operation state completes, and that x-operation-set will be raised if the user attempts to set another operation after having already set an operation for the current state.

Messages allocated on the heap are not copied when being set from one action to another. This avoids the expense of having to copy data from one buffer to another and the complexity of having to manage space to store messages to send or receive. In this way actions in zeptoscript differ from actions in zeptoforth. This also means that messages can be modified after they are sent or received, which in most cases will be undesirable; to avoid this use zscript::duplicate or zscript-list::duplicate-list if this would turn out to be an issue.

zscript-action words

make-schedule

( – schedule )

Create an empty schedule.

make-action

( init-xt – action )

Create an action with an initial state of init-xt.

add-action

( schedule action – )

Add action to schedule.

remove-action

( action – )

Remove action from its current schedule.

send-action-fail

( send-xt fail-xt data dest-action – ) send-xt: ( – ) fail-xt: ( – )

Set the current action to send a message data to dest-action, and call send-xt on success or fail-xt on failure.

send-action

( resume-xt data dest-action – ) resume-xt: ( – )

Set the current action to send a message data to dest-action, and call resume-xt afterwards regardless of success or failure.

send-action-timeout

( timeout-ticks send-xt fail-xt data dest-action – ) send-xt: ( – ) fail-xt: ( – )

Set the current action to send a message data to dest-action with a timeout of timeout-ticks, and call send-xt on success or fail-xt on failure.

recv-action

( recv-xt – ) recv-xt: ( data src-action – )

Set the current action to receive a message, and call recv-xt with received data from src-action on message receipt.

recv-action-timeout

( timeout-ticks recv-xt timeout-xt – ) recv-xt: ( data src-action – ) timeout-xt: ( – )

Set the current action to receive a message with a timeout of timeout-ticks, and call recv-xt with received data from src-action on message receipt, or timeout-xt on timeout.

delay-action

( ticks resume-xt – ) resume-xt: ( – )

Set the current action to wait ticks and then call resume-xt.

delay-action-from-time

( systick-start systick-delay resume-xt – ) resume-xt: ( – )

Set the current action to wait systick-delay ticks from systick-start ticks and th en call resume-xt.

yield-action

( resume-xt – ) resume-xt: ( – )

Set the current action to give up control and then call resume-xt when it regains control.

run-schedule

( schedule – )

Run the schedule and its actions.

stop-schedule

( schedule – )

Set the schedule to cleanly stop.

action-schedule@

( action – schedule )

Get the schedule of action.

in-schedule?

( action – flag )

Get whether an action is in a schedule.

current-schedule

( – schedule )

Get the current schedule.

current-action

( – action )

Get the current action.

x-already-in-schedule

( – )

Action already in schedule exception.

x-not-in-schedule

( – )

Action not in schedule exception.

x-schedule-already-running

( – )

Schedule already running exception.

x-operation-set

( – )

Action already has an operation set exception.

Arrays

zeptoscript has optional support for arrays. Arrays are like sequences (internally they simply wrap a sequence), but they may change length. They have four types, specifically cell arrays, cell array slices, byte arrays, and byte array slices.

Note that while arrays may be resized, repeated prepending of elements is still best accomplished with lists, and each time an array is concatenated a whole new underlying sequence is allocated and the elements from the original arrays are copied into it. However, arrays are more memory-efficient than lists, especially when long, as they consist simply of a backing sequence and a small wrapper.

zscript-array Words

array?

( x – array? )

Get whether something is an array.

cell-array?

( x – cell-array? )

Get whether something is a cell array.

byte-array?

( x – byte-array? )

Get whether something is a byte array.

array-seq@

( array – seq )

Get the underlying sequence in an array.

array>len

( array – len )

Get the length of an array.

wrap-seq-as-array

( seq – array )

Wrap a sequence in an array.

>cell-array

( x0 … xn count – array )

Create a cell array from the stack.

>byte-array

( c0 … cn count – array )

Create a byte array from the stack.

array>

( array – x0 … xn count )

Explode an array onto the stack.

#!

( – )

Begin defining a cell array.

!#

( – )

End defining a cell array.

#$

( – )

Begin defining a byte array.

$#

( – )

End defining a byte array.

array@

( index array – x )

Get an element of an array.

array!

( x index array – )

Set an element of an array.

duplicate-array

( array – array’ )

Duplicate an array.

concat-arrays

( array0 array1 – array2 )

Concatenate two cell or byte arrays.

concat!-arrays

( array0 array1 – )

Concatenate two cell or byte arrays in place.

seq>array

( seq – array )

Convert a sequence to an array, duplicating it.

array>seq

( array – seq )

Convert an array to a sequence, duplicating it.

array>slice

( offset count array – array’ )

Get a slice of an array.

array>slice!

( offset count array – )

Get a slice of an array in place.

truncate-start-array

( count array – array’ )

Truncate the start of an array as a slice.

truncate-end-array

( count array – array’ )

Truncate the end of an array as a slice.

truncate-start!-array

( count array – )

Truncate the start of an array in place as a slice.

truncate-end!-array

( count array – )

Truncate the end of an array in place as a slice.

iter-array

( array xt – )

Iterate over an array.

iteri-array

( array xt – )

Iterate over an array with an index.

find-index-array

( array xt – index found? ) xt: ( item – flag )

Get the index of an element that meets a predicate; note that the lowest matching index is returned, and xt will not necessarily be called against all items.

find-indexi-array

( array xt – index found? ) xt: ( item index – flag )

Get the index of an element that meets a predicate with an index; note that the lowest matching index is returned, and xt will not necessarily be called against all items.

map-array

( array xt – array’ ) xt: ( item – item’ )

Map a cell or byte array into a new cell or byte array.

mapi-array

( array xt – array’ ) xt: ( item – item’ )

Map a cell or byte array into a new cell or byte array with an index.

map!-array

( array xt – ) xt: ( item – item’ )

Map a cell or byte array in place.

mapi!-array

( array xt – ) xt: ( item – item’ )

Map a cell or byte array in place with an index.

filter-array

( array xt – array’ ) xt: ( item – item’ )

Filter a cell or byte array into a new cell or byte array.

filteri-array

( array xt – array’ ) xt: ( item – item’ )

Filter a cell or byte array into a new cell or byte array with an index.

filter!-array

( array xt – ) xt: ( item – item’ )

Filter a cell or byte array in place.

filteri!-array

( array xt – ) xt: ( item – item’ )

Filter a cell or byte array in place with an index.

foldl-array

( x array xt – x’ ) xt: ( x item – x’ )

Fold left over a cell or byte array.

foldli-array

( x array xt – x’ ) xt: ( x item index – x’ )

Fold left over a cell or byte array with an index.

foldr-array

( x array xt – x’ ) xt: ( item x – x’ )

Fold right over a cell or byte array.

foldri

( x array xt – x’ ) xt: ( item x index – x’ )

Fold right over a cell or byte array with an index.

collectl-cell-array

( x len xt – array ) xt: ( x – x item )

Collect elements of a cell array from left to right.

collectli-cell-array

( x len xt – array ) xt: ( x index – x item )

Collect elements of a cell array from left to right with an index.

collectr-cell-array

( x len xt – array ) xt: ( x – x item )

Collect elements of a cell array from right to left.

collectri-cell-array

( x len xt – array ) xt: ( x – x item )

Collect elements of a cell array from right to left with an index.

collectl-byte-array

( x len xt – array ) xt: ( x – x item )

Collect elements of a byte array from left to right.

collectli-byte-array

( x len xt – array ) xt: ( x index – x item )

Collect elements of a byte array from left to right with an index.

collectr-byte-array

( x len xt – array ) xt: ( x – x item )

Collect elements of a byte array from right to left.

collectri-byte-array

( x len xt – array ) xt: ( x – x item )

Collect elements of a byte array from right to left with an index.

reverse-array

( array – array’ )

Reverse an array producing a new array.

reverse!-array

( array – )

Reverse an array in place.

zip-arrays

( array0 array1 – array2 )

Zip two arrays into a new array, using the length of the shorter array.

zip3-arrays

( array0 array1 array2 – array3 )

Zip three arrays into a new array, using the length of the shorter array.

zip!-arrays

( array0 array1 – )

Zip two arrays into the first array in-place, using the length of the shorter array.

zip3!-arrays

( array0 array1 array2 – )

Zip three arrays into the first array in-place, using the length of the shorter array.

sort!-array

( array xt – )

Heapsort an array in place.

sort-array

( array xt – array’ )

Heapsort an array, copying it.

all-array

( array xt – all? ) xt: ( element – match? )

Get whether a predicate applies to all elements of a array; note that not all elements will be iterated over if an element returns false, and true will be returned if the array is empty.

alli-array

( array xt – all? ) xt: ( element index – match? )

Get whether a predicate applies to all elements of a array; note that not all elements will be iterated over if an element returns false, and true will be returned if the array is empty.

any-array

( array xt – any? ) xt: ( element – match? )

Get whether a predicate applies to any element of a array; note that not all elements will be iterated over if an element returns true, and false will be returned if the array is empty.

anyi-array

( array xt – any? ) xt: ( element index – match? )

Get whether a predicate applies to any element of a array; note that not all elements will be iterated over if an element returns true, and false will be returned if the array is empty.

split-array

( array xt – array’ ) xt: ( item – flag )

Split an array based on a predicate.

spliti-array

( array xt – array’ ) xt: ( item index – flag )

Split an array based on a predicate with an index.

split!-array

( array xt – ) xt: ( item – flag )

Split an array in place based on a predicate.

spliti!-array

( array xt – ) xt: ( item index – flag )

Split an array in place based on a predicate with an index.

join-arrays

( list-array join-array – array’ )

Join an array of arrays.

Channels

Channels are used by tasks to send each other messages. They consist of queues with fixed maximum numbers of elements.

If there are fewer elements than the maximum in a queue and a task attempts to send on a channel, the new element will be enqueued, and if a task is waiting to receive an element it will be woken up and will then receive the element; otherwise the sending task will block until another task receives from the queue to free up space for the new element.

If there are greater than zero elements in a queue and a task attempts to receive from a channel, the next element will be dequeued, and if a task is waiting to send an element it will be woken up and will then send the element; otherwise the receiving task will block until another task sends on the queue.

zscript-chan words

make-chan

( size – channel )

Create a channel with a maximum number of elements of size.

send

( message channel – )

Send a message to a channel. If the channel is full, block until a receiving task frees up space for the message. Also, if there are blocked receiving tasks, wake up one receiving task.

send-non-block

( message channel – success? ).

Send a message to a channel in a non-blocking fashion, If the channel has room to enqueue the message, return true, else return false.

recv

( channel – message )

Receive a message from a channel. If the channel is empty, block until a sending task provides a message to receive. Also, if there are blocked sending tasks, wake up one sending task.

recv-non-block

( channel – message success? )

Receive a message from a channel in a non-blocking fashion. If the channel is not empty, return the message and true, else return 0 and false.

peek

( channel – message )

Peek a message from a channel, i.e. read it without dequeuing it. If the channel is empty, block until a sending task provides a message to peek.

peek-non-block

( channel – message success? )

Peek a message from a channel, i.e. read it without dequeueing it, in a non-blocking fashion. If the channel is not empty, return the message and true, else return 0 and false.

zeptoscript Core Functionality

zeptoscript is a high-level, dynamically-typed language implemented on top of zeptoforth. It includes automatic memory management achieved through the use of a Cheney’s algorithm garbage collector.

zeptoscript has the following basic data types:

Integrals, with subtypes being nulls, small integers (i.e. 31-bit), and big integers (i.e. 32-bit); note that true and false are integrals, specifically -1 and 0.

Cell sequences

Cell slices

Byte sequences, with normal and constant subtypes

Byte slices

Execution tokens, with normal and closure subtypes

All three subtypes of integrals are handled transparently to the user, and can only be told apart when the user applies the word >type to them. However, in most cases the number 0 will be a null, all integers that can be unambiguously represented as two’s-complement numbers with 31 bits will be a small integer, and all integers that require a full 32 bits to be unambiguously represented will be a big integer. A key difference between nulls and small integers on one hand and bit integers on the other is that nulls and small integers are not allocated in the heap while big integers are; note that big integers require two cells to be stored for their heap allocation (in addition to any cells taken for references to them) while nulls and small integers only require one cell each.

Cell sequences, cell slices, non-constant byte sequences, and byte slices which have non-constant byte sequences as their backing store are mutable. Examples of words which may mutate these include !+ (for cell sequences and slices), and c!+, h!+, and w!+ (for byte sequences and slices). Other examples include map!, mapi!, zip!, zip3!, reverse!, and sort!, which transform sequences and slices in place. A general naming convention for mutating words is that they have ! in their names.

The difference between sequences and slices is that sequences comprise a backing store whereas slices are references to an offset and length within a sequence. Consequently, mutating a slice mutates its underlying sequence and any other slices which share part of the same data within the same underlying sequence. In many cases they are more efficient to use rather than physically duplicating a sequence or a part of one; however, if one wants to create a separate sequence (which may be mutated without mutating the original sequence) from a sequence or slice one should use duplicate ( seq - seq’ ), or another word that creates a new sequence from an existing one with a transformation, such as map, mapi, filter, filteri, zip, zip3, reverse, or sort.

Many of the operations work on all of cell sequences, cell slices, byte sequences (both normal and constant), and byte slices. However, there are exceptions; e.g. @+, !+, and cells> are only for cell sequences and slices while c@+, c!+, h@+, h!+, w@+, w!+, bytes>, and type are only for byte sequences and slices.

Execution tokens and closures are closely related. Both execution tokens and closures may be executed with the words execute, ?execute, and try; however, only execution tokens may be used as exceptions with ?raise. The words ;], ', and ['] create execution tokens, which reference code outside the zeptoscript heap which may be executed. The word bind ( xn … x0 count xt – closure ) takes an execution token xt and binds it to count values on the stack, producing a closure, which when executed will push values xn … x0 onto the stack prior to executing xt. Both execution tokens and closures live on the heap. Note, though, that there may be cases where one may need to convert between execution tokens and integrals referencing the addresses of their underlying code; these conversions are achieved with unsafe::integral>xt ( integral – xt ) and unsafe::xt>integral ( xt – integral ). These conversions may not be made with closures.

zeptoscript does not make use of standard Forth variable and value; while these are retained for legacy reasons they may only be used with extreme caution and are best avoided when possible. Rather, zeptoscript provides global ( “name” – ); unlike variable and value, the garbage collector is aware of globals, so potentially garbage-collected values can be stored in them, whereas it is very much unsafe to put allocated values, including big integers, in variables or values. Note that globals may be declared either when compiling to RAM or when compiling to flash.

Take the following for example:

global foo

This creates the following words:

A getter word foo@ ( – foo )

A setter word foo! ( foo – )

One feature of zeptoscript is records. Records are essentially syntactic sugar on top of cell sequences which provides accessor words for constructing, setting, and accessing cell sequences and their elements. In many cases it leads to more readable code than using >cells, cells>, @+, and !+ directly when one is using a cell sequence for purposes other than acting as a vector/array.

Take the following for example:

begin-record foo
  item: foo-x
  item: foo-y
  item: foo-z
end-record

This creates the following words:

A constructor word make-foo ( – foo ) for creating an empty (i.e. all null) record with three elements.

A constructor word >foo ( foo-x foo-y foo-z – foo ) for creating a record containing the specified elements popped off the stack

An exploding word foo> ( foo – foo-x foo-y foo-z ) which takes a record foo and pushes its elements onto the stack.

A word foo-size ( – size ) which pushes the size in elements of a foo record, in this case three.

The words foo-x@ ( foo – foo-x ), foo-y@ ( foo – foo-y ), and foo-z@ ( foo – foo-z ) for fetching named elements of foo.

The words foo-x! ( foo-x foo – ), foo-y! ( foo-y foo – ), and foo-z! ( foo-z foo – ) for setting named elements of foo.

Before zeptoscript can be used it must be initialized with zscript::init-zscript ( compile-size runtime-size – ). If this is done during compilation to flash compile-size is used for the heap size, otherwise runtime-size is used. Also, if this is done during compilation to flash an init routine is compiled to flash which initializes the heap to runtime-size next time the system is booted. Note that compile-size and runtime-size are rounded up to the nearest full multiple of eight bytes. All code to be compiled which is not zeptoscript code must be compiled before this point, as zscript::init-zscript overrides the numeric parser and thus will break non-zeptoscript code. Also, all code to be compiled which is zeptoscript code must be compiled after this point, as it will break otherwise (as compiling zeptoscript code outside of src/common/core.fs requires an initialized zeptoscript heap and numeric parser).

zeptoscript code may only execute in one task, because the zeptoscript garbage collector is only aware of the current task, and the synchronization necessary to achieve execution across tasks would prove problematic. However, for asynchronous programming, an action scheduler mechanism is provided by src/common/action.fs. This is similar to the zeptoforth action scheduler, but has a few minor differences (e.g. data transferred between actions is not copied aside from the copying of integral messages and references to allocated messages). The action scheduler is “stackless” in that every action shares the same underlying data and return stacks, and storing state information between states is accomplished through providing closures for each state, and in said closures referencing outside data.

S15.16 fixed-point numerics are provided by src/common/fixed32.fs. These fixed-point numbers are cell-sized so they fit in the space of normal integrals. Note that operations for addition, subtraction, and negation are not included in src/common/fixed32.fs. This is because normal integral +, -, and negate fits these roles. Note that loading src/common/fixed32.fs overrides the numeric parser to enable parsing S15.16 literals, which have the form x;y where ; is the decimal point.

Words

null-type

( – type )

The null type.

int-type

( – type )

The small integer type.

bytes-type

( – type )

The non-constant byte sequence type.

word-type

( – type )

The big integer type.

2word-type

( – type )

The double-cell type (for future use).

const-bytes-type

( – type )

The constant byte sequence type.

xt-type

( – type )

The execution token type.

tagged-type

( – type )

A type for auxiliary types, such as words.

cells-type

( – type )

The cell sequence type.

closure-type

( – type )

The closure type.

slice-type

( – type )

The slice type; note that this encompasses slices of cell sequences, non-constant byte sequences, and constant byte sequences.

raw-lit,

( x – )

Compile an integral value as a raw literal which, when executed, will push its value as a zeptoforth integral value rather than a zeptoscript integral value.

lit,

( x – )

Compile an integral value as a literal which, when executed, will push its value as a zeptoscript integral value.

addr-len>const-bytes

( c-addr len – const-bytes )

Create a constant byte sequence from a non-volatile address and length; this is intended for string literals compiled into code.

addr-len>bytes

( c-addr len – bytes )

Create a non-constant byte sequence from a potentially-volatile address and length; when creating byte sequences from raw data which is not compiled into code this is normally what you would want.

>raw

( x – x’ )

Get the raw backing store of a cell sequence, byte sequence, or slice value. The primary purpose of this is for converting slices into their underlying cell or byte sequences.

>raw-offset

( x – offset )

Get the raw offset of a cell sequence, byte sequence, or slice value. The primary purpose of this is for determining where a slice points into its underlying cell or byte sequence.

>len

( x – len )

Get the length of a cell sequence, byte sequence, or slice in entries or bytes.

>pair

( x0 x1 – pair )

Create a two-element cell sequence from a pair of values.

pair>

( pair – x0 x1 )

Explode a two-element cell sequence or slice into a pair of values.

>triple

( x0 x1 x2 – triple )

Create a three-element cell sequence from three values.

triple>

( triple – x0 x1 x2 )

Explode a three-element cell sequence or slice into three values.

make-cells

( count – cells )

Create a cell sequence with the specified element count that is initialized to null.

make-bytes

( count – bytes )

Create a byte sequence with the specified byte count that is initialized to null.

>cells

( xn … x0 count – cells )

Create a cell sequence with count elements taken off the stack.

>bytes

( cn … c0 count – bytes )

Create a byte sequence with count bytes taken off the stack.

cells>

( cells – xn … x0 count )

Explode a cell sequence or slice into elements and a count on the stack.

bytes>

( bytes – cn … c0 count )

Explode a byte sequence or slice into bytes and a count on the stack.

cells-no-count>

( cells – xn … x0 )

Explode a cell sequence or slice into elements on the stack.

bytes-no-count>

( bytes – cn … c0 )

Explode a byte sequence or slice into bytes on the stack.

@+

( index cells – x )

Get the element at index, indexed from zero, of a cell sequence or slice.

!+

( x index cells – )

Set the elememt at index, indexed from zero, of a cell sequence or slice.

w@+

( index bytes – x )

Get the cell at index, indexed from zero and word-aligned, of a byte sequence or slice.

w!+

( x index bytes – )

Set the cell at index, indexed from zero and word-aligned, of a non-constant byte sequence or slice.

h@+

( index bytes – h )

Get the halfword at index, indexed from zero and halfword-aligned, of a byte sequence or slice.

h!+

( h index bytes – )

Set the halfword at index, indexed from zero and halfword-aligned, of a non-constant byte sequence or slice.

c@+

( index bytes – c )

Get the byte at index, indexed from zero, of a byte sequence or slice.

c!+

( c index bytes – )

Set the byte at index, indexed from zero, of a non-constant byte sequence or slice.

x@+

( index cells|bytes – x )

Get the element or byte at index, indexed from zero, of a cell or byte sequence or slice.

x!+

( x index cells|bytes – )

Set the elememt or byte at index, indexed from zero, of a non-constant cell or byte sequence or slice.

cells?

( x – cells? )

Get whether a value is a cell sequence or slice.

bytes?

( x – bytes? )

Get whether a value is a byte sequence or slice.

init-zscript

( compile-size runtime-size – )

Initialize zeptoscript. All non-zeptoscript code must be compiled before this word is called, and all zeptoscript code must be compiled after this word is called. If called during compilation to flash, a call to this word will be compiled into the initialization process on bootup, so zeptoscript will automatically be initialized after the previous definition of init (or declaration of an initializer) and before any subsequent definitions of init (or declarations of initializer). Note that when compiling to flash the zeptoscript heap size will be initialized to compile-size, but when compiling to RAM or on any subsequent boot the zeptoscript heap size will be initialized to runtime-size. Note that the heap size is rounded up to the nearest eight bytes.

copy

( value0 offset0 value1 offset1 count – )

Do a shallow copy of count elements or bytes from one cell or byte sequence or slice to another, starting at offset0 of value0 to offset1 of value1. All offsets are indexed from zero. value0 and value1 must both be either cell sequences or slices or byte sequences or slices; copying between cell sequences or slices and byte sequences or slices is not permitted. Also note that value1 cannot be a constant byte sequence or slice.

s"

( “string” – bytes )

Create a string literal as a byte sequence; note that if compiled the resulting byte sequence is constant, whereas if immediate the resulting byte sequence is non-constant.

s\"

Create a string literal with escapes as a byte sequence; note that if compiled the resulting byte sequence is constant, whereas if immediate the resulting byte sequence is non-constant.

+

( x0 x1 – x2 )

Add two integers.

1+

( x0 – x1 )

Add one to an integer.

cell+

( x0 – x1 )

Add a cell, i.e. four, to an integer.

-

( x0 x1 – x2 )

Subtract two integers.

1-

( x0 x1 – x2 )

Subtract one from an integer.

*

( x0 x1 – x2 )

Multiply two integers.

2*

( x0 – x1 )

Multiply an integer by two.

4*

( x0 – x1 )

Multiply an integer by four.

cells

( x0 – x1 )

Multiply an integer by a cell.

/

( n0 n1 – n2 )

Divide two signed integers.

2/

( n0 – n1 )

Divide a signed integer by two.

4/

( n0 – n1 )

Divide a signed integer by four.

u/

( u0 u1 – u2 )

Divide two unsigned integers.

mod

( n0 n1 – n2 )

Get the modulus of two signed integers.

umod

( u0 u1 – u2 )

Get the modulus of two unsigned integers.

negate

( n0 – n1 )

Negate an integer.

or

( x0 x1 – x2 )

Or two integers.

and

( x0 x1 – x2 )

And two integers.

xor

( x0 x1 – x2 )

Exclusive-or two integers.

bic

( x0 x1 – x2 )

Clear bits in an integer.

not

( x0 – x1 )

Not an integer.

invert

( x0 – x1 )

Invert an integer.

lshift

( x0 x1 – x2 )

Left shift an integer.

rshift

( x0 x1 – x2 )

Logical right shift an integer.

arshift

( x0 x1 – x2 )

Arithmetic right shift an integer.

align

( x0 x1 – x2 )

Align a value to a power of two.

=

( x0 x1 – flag )

Get whether two values are equal. Integral values are compared for their values, even in the case of big integers. Execution tokens are compared for their underlying code addresses. All other values are compared for their addresses in memory.

<>

( x0 x1 – flag )

Get whether two values are unequal. Integral values are compared for their values, even in the case of big integers. Execution tokens are compared for their underlying code addresses. All other values are compared for their addresses in memory.

<

( n0 n1 – flag )

Signed less than.

>

( n0 n1 – flag )

Signed greater than.

<=

( n0 n1 – flag )

Signed less than or equal.

>=

( n0 n1 – flag )

Signed greater than or equal.

u<

( u0 u1 – flag )

Unsigned less than.

u>

( u0 u1 – flag )

Unsigned greater than.

u<=

( u0 u1 – flag )

Unsigned less than or equal.

u>=

( u0 u1 – flag )

Unsigned greater than or equal.

u<

( u0 u1 – flag )

Unsigned less than.

u>

( u0 u1 – flag )

Unsigned greater than.

u<=

( u0 u1 – flag )

Unsigned less than or equal.

u>=

( u0 u1 – flag )

Unsigned greater than or equal.

0=

( x – flag )

Equal to zero; note that for non-integral values false is returned.

0<>

( x – flag )

Not equal to zero; note that for non-integral values true is returned.

0<

( n – flag )

Less than zero.

0>

( n – flag )

Greater than zero.

0<=

( n – flag )

Less than or equal to zero.

0>=

( n – flag )

Greater than or equal to zero.

min

( n0 n1 – n2 )

Get the minimum of two numbers.

max

( n0 n1 – n2 )

Get the maximum of two numbers.

cell

( – u )

The size of a cell, i.e. four.

if

( x – )

If conditional; note that non-integral values are treated as true.

while

( x – )

While conditional; note that non-integral values are treated as true.

until

( x – )

Until conditional; note that non-integral values are treated as true.

?do

( end start – )

Start do loop; note that this is redefined because of the chance that two vales may be equal but have different types.

loop

( – )

Close a do loop.

+loop

( increment – )

Close a do loop with an increment.

case

( x – )

Start a case block.

of

( x – )

Start an of block.

.

( n – )

Print a signed integer with a following space.

u.

( u – )

Print an unsigned integer with a following space.

(.)

( n – )

Print a signed integer without a following space.

(u.)

( u – )

Print an unsigned integer without a following space.

emit

( c – )

Print a character.

h.1

( x – )

Print the lowest four bits of an unsigned integer as one hexadecimal digit.

h.2

( x – )

Print the lowest eight bits of an unsigned integer as two hexadecimal digits.

h.4

( x – )

Print the lowest sixteen bits of an unsigned integer as four hexadecimal digits.

h.8

( x – )

Print an unsigned integer as eight hexadecimal digits.

h.16

( d – )

Print a double cell unsigned integer as sixteen hexadecimal digits.

spaces

( x – )

Print x spaces.

>slice

( offset length seq – slice )

Get an arbitrary slice of a sequence or slice of length starting at offset.

truncate-start

( count seq – slice )

Get a slice of a sequence or slice truncating count elements or bytes from the start.

truncate-end

( count seq – slice )

Get a slice of a sequence or slice truncating count elements or bytes from the end.

>type

( x – type )

Get the type of a value.

integral?

( x – integral? )

Get whether a value is integral.

small-int?

( x – small-int? )

Get whether a value is a small integer or null.

token

( runtime: “name” – seq | 0 )

Parse a token and return it as a byte sequence, or return 0 if no token could be parsed.

token-word

( runtime: “name” – word )

Parse a token and get the corresponding word; note that an exception will be raised if there is no token or the word cannot be found.

word>xt

( word – xt )

Get an execution token corresponding to a word.

;]

( – xt )

End a quotation (also known as a lambda) and, if compiling, compile pushing the execution token, or otherwise immediately pushing the execution token.

execute

( xt | closure – )

Execute an execution token or closure. If a closure is executed, push the bound values onto the stack prior to executing the underlying execution token.

try

( xt | closure – exception | 0 )

Execute an execution token or closure like execute, but catching any exceptions that are raised. If an exception is raised it is returned, otherwise 0 is returned.

?execute

( xt | closure | 0 – )

If a non-zero value is provided it is executed like with execute, otherwise it is ignored.

type

( seq – )

Type a string.

'

( “name” – xt )

Get an xt at interpretation-time.

[']

( ‘name” – xt )

Get an xt at compile-time.

?raise

( xt – )

Raise an exception.

averts

( f “name” – )

Assert that a value is true, otherwise raise a specified exception.

triggers

( f “name” – )

Assert that a value is false, otherwise raise a specified exception.

raise

( “name” – )

Always raise an exception; this is needed due to issues with compiling code.

start-compile

( seq – )

Start compiling a word with a name.

end-compile,

( – )

End compiling, exported to match start-compile.

constant-with-name

( x name – )

Define a constant with a name.

raw-constant-with-name

( x name – )

Define a raw constant with a name.

[char]

( “name” – x )

Redefine [CHAR].

char

( “name” – x )

Redefine CHAR.

begin-record

( “name” – token offset )

Begin declaring a record.

end-record

( token offset – )

Finish declaring a record.

item:

( offset “name” – offset’ )

Create a field in a record.

foreign-constant

( “foreign-name” “new-name” – )

Make a foreign constant.

foreign-variable

( “foreign-name” “new-name” – )

Make a foreign variable.

foreign

( in-count out-count “foreign-name” “new-name” – )

Make a foreign word usable.

execute-foreign

( in-count out-count xt – )

Execute a foreign word.

find

( seq – word|0 )

Find a word.

find-all-dict

( seq word – word’|0 )

Find a word in a dictionary in all wordlists.

flash-latest

( – word )

Get the latest word in flash.

ram-latest

( – word )

Get the latest word in RAM.

latest

( – word )

Get the latest word.

state?

( – state? )

Get the compilation state.

+to

( x “name” – )

Add to a local or a VALUE.

constant

( x “name” – )

Define a CONSTANT.

2constant

( x0 x1 “name” – )

Define a 2CONSTANT.

global

( “name” – )

Create a global.

bind

( xn … x0 count xt – closure )

Bind a scope to a lambda.

pick

( xn … x0 u – x )

Redefine PICK.

roll

( xn … x0 u – xn-1 … x0 xn u )

Redefine ROLL.

base!

( base – )

Set BASE.

base@

( – base )

Get BASE.

with-base

( base xt – )

Execute an xt with a BASE.

parse-integer

( seq – n success )

Parse an integer.

duplicate

( seq0 – seq1 )

Duplicate a cell or byte sequence; this converts slices to non-slices and constant byte sequences into non-constant byte sequences.

concat

( seq0 seq1 – seq2 )

Concatenate two cell or byte sequences.

iter

( seq xt – )

Iterate over a cell sequence.

iteri

( seq xt – )

Iterate over a cell sequence with an index.

map

( seq xt – seq’ )

Map a cell or byte sequence into a new cell sequence.

mapi

( seq xt – seq’ )

Map a cell or byte sequence into a new cell sequence with an index.

map!

( seq xt – )

Map a cell or byte sequence in place.

mapi!

( seq xt – )

Map a cell or byte sequence in place with an index.

make-bits

( len – bits )

Make a zeroed bit sequence.

bits>len

( bits – len )

Get the length of bits.

bit!

( bit index bits – )

Set a bit in a bit sequence.

bit@

( index bits – )

Get a bit in a bit sequence.

filter

( seq xt – seq’ )

Filter a cell or byte sequence.

filteri

( seq xt – seq’ )

Filter a cell or byte sequence with an index.

foldl

( x seq xt – x’ ) xt: ( x item – x’ )

Fold left over a cell or byte sequence.

foldli

( x seq xt – x’ ) xt: ( x item index – x’ )

Fold left over a cell or byte sequence with an index.

foldr

( x seq xt – x’ ) xt: ( item x – x’ )

Fold right over a cell or byte sequence.

foldri

( x seq xt – x’ ) xt: ( item x index – x’ )

Fold right over a cell or byte sequence with an index.

reverse

( seq – seq’ )

Reverse a sequence producing a new sequence.

reverse!

( seq – )

Reverse a sequence in place.

zip

( seq0 seq1 – seq2 )

Zip two sequences into a new sequence, using the length of the shorter sequence.

zip3

( seq0 seq1 seq2 – seq3 )

Zip three sequences into a new sequence, using the length of the shorter sequence.

zip!

( seq0 seq1 – )

Zip two sequences into the first sequence in-place; note that if the ranges do not match an exception is raised, and the first sequence must be a cell sequence.

zip3!

( seq0 seq1 seq2 – )

Zip three sequences into the first sequence in-place; note that if the ranges do not match an exception is raised, and the first sequence must be a cell sequence.

sort!

( seq xt – )

Heapsort a cell or byte sequence in place.

sort

( seq xt – )

Heapsort a cell or byte sequence, copying it.

all

( seq xt – all? )

Get whether a predicate applies to all elements of a sequence; note that not all elements will be iterated over if an element returns false, and true will be returned if the sequence is empty.

any

( seq xt – any? )

Get whether a predicate applies to any element of a sequence; note that not all elements will be iterated over if an element returns true, and false will be returned if the sequence is empty.

join

( list-seq join-seq – seq’ )

Join a cell sequence of cell or byte sequences.

depth

( – depth )

Get the current depth.

#(

( – )

Start defining a cell sequence.

#<

( – )

Start defining a byte sequence.

)#

( xn … x0 – cells )

Finish definining a cell sequence.

>#

( cn … c0 – bytes )

Finish defining a byte sequence.

0cells

( – cells )

Empty cell sequence.

0bytes

( – bytes )

Empty byte sequence.

unsafe words

bytes>addr-len

( bytes – addr len )

Get the starting address and length of a byte sequence or slice. Note that these are not guaranteed to remain constant with any subsequent allocations that may trigger the garbage collector.

@

( addr – x )

Redefine @.

!

( x addr – )

Redefine !.

+!

( x addr – )

Redefine +!.

bis!

( x addr – )

Redefine BIS!.

bic!

( x addr – )

Redefine BIC!.

xor!

( x addr – )

Redefine XOR!.

h@

( addr – h )

Redefine H@.

h!

( h addr – )

Redefine H!.

h+!

( h addr – )

Redefine H+!.

hbis!

( x addr – )

Redefine HBIS!.

hbic!

( x addr – )

Redefine HBIC!.

hxor!

( x addr – )

Redefine HXOR!.

c@

( addr – c )

Redefine C@.

c!

( c addr – )

Redefine C!.

c+!

( c addr – )

Redefine C+!.

cbis!

( x addr – )

Redefine CBIS!.

fill

( addr bytes val – )

Redefine FILL.

>integral

( x – value )

Cast a value to an integer.

integral>

( value – x )

Cast a value from an integer.

2>integral

( x0 x1 – value0 value1 )

Cast two values to integers.

2integral>

( value0 value1 – x0 x1 )

Cast two values from integers.

xt>integral

( xt – value )

Convert an xt to an integral.

integral>xt

( value – xt )

Convert an integral to an xt.

here

( – x )

Get the HERE pointer.

allot

( x – )

ALLOT space.

Tasks

zeptoscript supports cooperative multitasking, distinct from zeptoforth’s preemptive multitasking. zeptoscript tasks all share a single zeptoforth task and a single zeptoscript heap. zeptoscript tasks execute in a round-robin fashion without priorities. Through the use of saved states each task has practically separate data and return stacks, even though they share their parent zeptoforth task’s data and return stack underneath it all.

zscript-task words

spawn

( task – )

Spawn a task which will execute task when executed.

yield

( – )

Yield the currently running task, adding it to the schedule and executing the next task ready to be executed. Note that if there are no other tasks ready to run this will return immediately.

terminate

( – )

Execute the next ready task without rescheduling the current task; note that this returns if there is no next ready task.

fork

( – parent? )

Fork the current task into two tasks, returning true for the parent task and false for the child task.

start

( – )

Start executing scheduled tasks, if there are any. If there are scheduled tasks, this does not return.

wake

( queue – )

If there are any tasks in a queue, dequeue the next task from the queue and schedule it.

block

( queue – )

If there are any tasks ready to execute, enqueue the current task into the queue and execute the next ready task.

wait-delay

( start-time delay – )

Wait for delay ticks after start-time ticks.

ms – )

( ms – )

Wait for ms milliseconds

Unbounded channels

Unbounded channels are used by tasks to send each other messages. They consist of queues with an unlimited number of elements.

Sending on an unbounded channel always returns immediately. The new element will be enqueued, and if a task is waiting to receive an element it will be woken up and will then receive the element; otherwise the element will remain queued for the next task to receive it. Note that as sending on unbounded channels never blocks, the only way to guarantee that the receiving task will actually receive the element is to call zscript-task::yield after sending on the ubnounded channels.

If there are greater than zero elements in a queue and a task attempts to receive from an unbonded channel, the next element will be dequeued; otherwise the receiving task will block until another task sends on the queue.

zscript-uchan words

make-uchan

( – uchannel )

Create an unbounded channel.

send

( message uchannel – )

Send a message to an unbounded channel. If there are blocked receiving tasks, wake up one receiving task. Note that this always returns immediately.

recv

( uchannel – message )

Receive a message from a unbounded channel. If the unbounded channel is empty, block until a sending task provides a message to receive.

recv-non-block

( uchannel – message success? )

Receive a message from a unbounded channel in a non-blocking fashion. If the unbounded channel is not empty, return the message and true, else return 0 and false.

peek

( uchannel – message )

Peek a message from a unbounded channel, i.e. read it without dequeuing it. If the unbounded channel is empty, block until a sending task provides a message to peek.

peek-non-block

( uchannel – message success? )

Peek a message from a unbounded channel, i.e. read it without dequeueing it, in a non-blocking fashion. If the unbounded channel is not empty, return the message and true, else return 0 and false.

Weak references

Weak references are values that embody references which do not protect referenced values from garbage collection, and are aware of when said referenced values are garbage collected. A value that is only weakly referenced, i.e. its chains of references at some points contain only weak references, is guaranteed to be garbage collected at the next garbage collection cycle. In this way they differ from Java “soft” references, which are may be followed for garbage collection purposes except when memory is tight.

There are two types of weak references, single weak references and weak pairs. Single weak references are simply references to individual values. Weak pairs are pairs of a weak reference to a value and a strong reference to another value. The utility of weak pairs is that they enable constructing linked lists of weak references.

zscript-weak words

broken-weak

( – symbol )

This symbol is a special value which represents a broken weak reference. Note that setting a weak reference to this value will not have the intended effect, because then weak-broken? will return false for a weak reference.

weak?

( x – flag )

Get whether a value is a single weak reference or a weak pair.

weak-pair?

( x – flag )

Get whether a value is a weak pair.

>weak

( x – weak )

Construct a single weak reference for a value x.

>weak-pair

( x y – weak-pair )

Construct a weak pair with a weak reference to x and a strong reference to y.

weak@

( weak – x )

Get the weakly referenced value for a weak reference; if the weak reference is broken, return broken-weak.

weak!

( x weak – )

Set the weakly referenced value for a weak reference. This can “repair” a broken weak reference.

weak-broken?

( weak – flag )

Get whether a weak reference is broken.

weak-pair-tail@

( weak-pair – tail )

Get the “tail”, i.e. the strong reference, of a weak pair.

weak-pair-tail!

( tail weak-pair – )

Set the “tail”, i.e. the strong reference, of a weak pair.